Guide to the Jack Morton papers, 1938-1993 MS2044
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Jack Morton papers
1938-1993
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Morton, Jack
MS2044
2.5 Linear Feet
Jack Morton Papers consists of four series of materials. The materials cover the period from the 1938-93, with the bulk of these raniging in date from 1983-90. The collection relates to the history of Jack Morton Productions, a business entertainment and meeting production company, and to the life of its founder, Jack Morton.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Biographical Note
Jack Morton (1910-2004) was an event marketing pioneer who founded Jack Morton Productions in 1939 in Washington, DC. The agency has grown to become Jack Morton Worldwide (www.jackmorton.com).
Morton born on June 6, 1910, in Newport, North Carolina, the fifth child of Irvin Leonidas Morton and Gertrude Riggs Morton. Named Irvin Leonidas Morton, Jr., he was called I.L. for much of his childhood, but picked up the nickname Jack as a young man. For the first six years of his life, he lived with his family on a sharecropper's farm in Wilson, North Carolina. After his mother's death he moved from one relative to another, staying with each for short periods of time until he moved out on his own as a late teenager.
Morton's first job in the entertainment industry was at the World Theater in Wilson, where he worked as the ticket-taker, usher, music coordinator, and bill poster from the age of twelve. Undertaking these jobs at various theaters led to his assuming the management of the Carolina Theater in Hamlet, North Carolina at age seventeen.
Because of his family circumstances, Morton's education was repeatedly interrupted. He finished high school in the spring of 1932 and went to Washington, D.C. at the suggestion of his employer, Western Electric. There, he served as the liaison between theater managers and Western Electric engineers who installed early theater sound systems. While employed with Western Electric, he enrolled at The George Washington University and went on to graduate with a B.A. from the Columbian College in 1936.
While an undergraduate at The George Washington University, Morton began booking orchestras and bands for fraternity and sorority dances. After he married Anne Morton in September of 1936 he briefly left the booking business for a stint as a refrigeration equipment salesman. But in October of 1938 he returned to the Washington, D.C. area and founded an entertainment booking business known as Jack Morton Enterprises. While Morton continued to book orchestras for college dances, he went on to include other venues such as hotels, night clubs, and resorts. Here too, Jack and Anne Morton raised three children, Bill, Dianne and Mary Lou.
Morton's business continued to expand after World War II with the beginning of the large business convention. His first big convention job was a show for the American Trucking Association, where he began to develop a fine reputation as a convention producer. Jack Morton prided himself on booking skilled, professional talent and has had a personal association with many big names in the show business world, including Bob Hope, Jack Benny, George Burns, Bob Newhart, and Alan King. In the late 1940's Morton's business expanded beyond the Washington Metropolitan Region with the opening of additional offices in New York, Chicago, Houston, San Francisco, and Atlanta.
In 1962, Jack Morton invited his son Bill to join him in the business and he helped in expanding the company to include audio-visual productions. Jack Morton Productions (JMP), as it is known today, has gone on to become a full-service corporate communication agency, producing entertainment programs, training programs, audio-visuals, and videoconferences for a variety of corporations and trade associations. Although he is retired from the business, Mr. Morton continues to offer his advice on company matters to his son and others at JMP.
He died June 28, 2004 at his home in Vero Beach, Florida.
Collection Scope and Content
The Jack Morton Papers consists of four series of materials. The materials cover the period from the 1938-93, with the bulk of these raniging in date from 1983-90. The collection relates to the history of Jack Morton Productions, a business entertainment and meeting production company, and to the life of its founder, Jack Morton.
In the first series of the collection are drafts, correspondence, photographs, and other items relating to the publication of Morton's autobiography, "The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story" and other articles and pamphlets. The second series of the collection contains materials related to the history of Jack Morton Productions, Morton's company. Included here are materials such as correspondence, company brochures, programs of events, entertainment booking guides and client lists, clippings, in-house company publications, and company advertising. The most serious limitation of this part of the collection is that there are no complete sets of materials. While the items contained in this series will give the user some idea of the range of events produced by the company, there is not enough material to give a broad understanding of the company's development and influence on the entertainment world.
There are two small series at the end of the collection. In the first series are videotapes of a Morton interview and his remarks at a JMP meeting. The second series is a miscellaneous group of materials that did not fit elsewhere in the collection.
Collection Organization
Organized into four series: Publications, Jack Morton Productions, Videotapes, Miscellaneous.
Photographs; Business; Entertainment events; Washington (D.C.); Videotapes; Benny, Jack; Jack Morton Productions; Burns, George; Hope, Bob; Morton, Jack
- Publications, 1983-1993; MS2044 Series 1; 1.5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of drafts, correspondence, photographs, and a final copy of Jack Morton's autobiography, "The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story." These materials relating to the production of his book are arranged by chapter according to the different draft copies, while other materials represent stages in the publishing process.
  Other materials include several pamphlets, articles and an essay entitled "The Poor Man's Philosopher," all published by Mr. Morton; as well as draft copies of an unpublished book on humor.
  Materials within this series range in date from 1983-93.
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story: Early untitled draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story: Early untitled draft continued, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story: Early untitled draft continued, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story: Early untitled draft continued, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story: Early untitled draft continued, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story: Early untitled draft continued, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story: Early untitled draft continued, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story: Early untitled draft continued, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story: Draft of memoirs as told to William Fuchs - Foreword; chapters 1, 2, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story: Draft of memoirs as told to William Fuchs - chapters 3, 4, 5, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story: Draft of memoirs as told to William Fuchs - chapters 6, 7, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story: Draft of memoirs as told to William Fuchs - chapters 8, 9, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story: Draft of memoirs as told to William Fuchs - chapters 10, 11, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story: Draft of memoirs as told to William Fuchs - chapters 12, 13, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story: Draft of memoirs as told to William Fuchs - chapters 14, 15, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story: Draft of memoirs as told to William Fuchs - chapters 16, 17, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story: Draft of memoirs as told to William Fuchs - chapters 18, 19, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story: Draft of memoirs as told to William Fuchs - chapters 20, 21, 22, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story draft - Foreword, chapters 1, 2, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story draft - chapters 3, 4, 5, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story draft - chapters 6, 7, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story draft - chapters 8, 9, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story draft - chapters 10, 11, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story draft - chapters 12, 13, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story draft - chapters 14, 15, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story draft - chapters 16, 17, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story draft - chapters 18, 19, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story draft - chapters 20, 21, 22, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story: Vantage Press correspondence about book, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story: Vantage Press correspondence about book, 1985-1989 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story: Photocopies of requests for testimonial letters for inclusion in book, 1982-1984 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story: Photocopies of testimonial letters for inclusion in book, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story: Photocopy of photograph and letter from Bob Hope for use in book, 1984 April 26 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story: Photocopies of possible dust jacket blurbs for book, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story: Photocopies of letter insets for use in book, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story: Prints of photographs used in book, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story: Other photographs (not used in book), undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story: Photographs of Wilson, North Carolina by William Fuchs (not used in book), undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story: Negatives, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Summary of Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Marketing information for Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story: Book announcement clipping, 1985 August 16 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Copy of The Jack Morton (Who's He?) Story, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Articles: "The Professional's Recipe for Producing a Good Show," in Executive Update, 1984 June (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Articles: Section outline for "Getting Ahead by Getting Along," n.d., undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Articles: "Getting Ahead by Getting Along," with biographical sketch, "About the Author,", 1989 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Articles: Marketing letter and lists for "Getting Ahead by Getting Along", 1989 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Pamphlets: How to Sell Yourself and All Sorts of Things, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Pamphlets: How to Talk on Your Feet and not Fall on Your - - -! A Quick Guide to Public Speaking, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - The Poor Man's Philosopher: Correspondence, 1993 March 17-June 03 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - The Poor Man's Philosopher: Typeset manuscript, 1993 May 11 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Copy of The Poor Man's Philosopher, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Unpublished Book on Humor: Outline draft, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Unpublished Book on Humor: Outline draft with additional handwritten and typescript material, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Unpublished Book on Humor: Incomplete draft of The Little Book on Humor, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Unpublished Book on Humor: Laughter, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Unpublished Book on Humor: Typed draft, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Unpublished Book on Humor: Handwritten draft of chapter 14, Technical aids, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Unpublished Book on Humor: Pitfalls of humor, 1989 June 21 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Unpublished Book on Humor: Retyped draft and handwritten additions, 1989 November 30 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Jack Morton productions, 1947-1993; MS2044 Series 2; 0.5 Linear feet
  This series of materials are related to the history of Jack Morton Productions, an event management and business meeting entertainment production company. The materials range in date from 1947-93.
  The materials, which include correspondence, company brochures, news clippings, company advertisements, in-house company publications, programs for events, and client lists, are incomplete and present only a random view of the workings of the company.
  - Correspondence, 1949-1957 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1958-1965 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1969-1979 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1983 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1991-1993 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - General Company Materials: Two early business cards, 1938-1939 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - General Company Materials: Company brochures, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - General Company Materials: Assorted business forms, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - General Company Materials: Membership update form for Greater Washington Society of Association Executives, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - General Company Materials: Communicator, random issues, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - General Company Materials: JMP Insider, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - General Company Materials: Two press releases, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Advertisements, 1950-1960 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Advertisements, 1960-1970 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Advertisements, 1970-1980 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Advertisements, 1950-1970 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Handwritten ideas for advertisements, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Clippings: Nation's Business, 1955 March (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1960-1993 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Entertainment Booking: Music and Entertainment Guide, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Entertainment Booking: JMP Client lists, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Entertainment Booking: Client lists, other agencies, 1976-1985 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Event Memorabilia: Photocopy of ticket to XON Annual Dance, 1947 November 05 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Event Memorabilia: Souvenir program for "Dinner with Ike,", 1960 January 27 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Event Memorabilia: Invitations to JMP events, 1980-1986 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Event Memorabilia: Program for GWSAE June Monthly Luncheon and Monument Awards, 1990 June 21 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Videotapes, 1993; MS2044 Series 3; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series contains videotapes of an interview conducted of Morton in Vero Beach, Florida, and a set of remarks Morton made at the Atlanta office of Jack Morton Productions in 1993.
  - Vero Beach interview, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Remarks by Jack Morton at JMP Atlanta, 1993 March 24 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Miscellaneous, Circa 1950-1990; MS2044 Series 4; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series contains three folders that did not fit with other collection materials, including two typewritten pages on booking different kinds of entertainment acts, a couple of photographs of Jack Morton, and a speech to Highland High School Graduates. The materials range in date from ca.1950-90.
  - Speech to Highland High School Graduates, 1990 June 06 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Photograph and proof sheet of photographs of Jack Morton, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Two pages typescript on booking acts, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)